ion is such a toxic element everybody
should know their ion status their ion
levels okay so welcome back to the trt
and hormone optimization YouTube channel
and back with us is Dr Rudy eberwine
welcome back
Rudy so happy to be here Stephen always
a good time together welcome back and a
few weeks ago we talked about iron
overload and fertin levels and you asked
me to send you my most recent blood
results and um yeah let's talk about
those first and um what that does it all
mean definitely so so I received your
your your iron levels and again you gave
me permission to go over that so no Hipp
violation um and that is something
important that you know for people
listening to this I'm pretty sure most
people did never did not get their iron
levels tested unless you ask for it
specifically they won't test it and
sometimes they'll test just the iron and
CIBC and they won't test the fertin so
I'd like everybody listening here and
then I'll make my argument why this is
important everybody should know their
ion status their ion levels it is as
important if not important then knowing
your cholesterol level your blood
glucose level your hemoglobin A1c your
hscp so ion level should be part of the
biohacking Age Management anti-aging
biomarker panel because it has such an
influence on chronic diseases and as I'm
going to prove to you
longevity right of those lap test that
you did is that the first time you ever
had your iron checked no I I I have that
I have it checked each year very good
and that's again a very Pro again
because you you know this I only started
checking iron about a year and a half on
my patients and I'm going to tell you
why I started checking iron levels it
was mostly because some guys were over
donating blood and they were dropping
their fiin so I went there looking for
low fertin levels but I found mostly
high fertin levels or higher than normal
fertin levels and this is where I
started really doing a deep dive into
understanding iron physiology
understanding the relationship between
iron and testosterone and chronic
diseases overall and this is what we're
going to talk about today
so yeah before you go over my blood
blood work I must First share with the
viewers that of course I'm on trt and um
I've never donated blood rity so that I
want to share good good and your levels
show that really your levels are are
pretty good so we you you sent me a
compilation of your Labs do do you have
them with you by any chance um no I
don't I remember so your iron level was
75 uh which was within normal limits
your transfering or iron saturation was
26% which is within normal limits us
usually we wanted between 15 or 20 up to
50% you know between 20 and 45 would be
ideal and your fertin which is what
we're going to spend a lot of time
talking about your fertin level was 140
normal fertin on most lab ranges for
example Lab Corp in the US that we're
using the normal fertin level are 30 to
400 nanogram per met per per milliliter
and that's for men for women it's from
20 to 150 but we're going to speak
mostly about men and when I speak about
iron deficiency I'll talk more about
women so normal Fair on paper is 30 to
400 kind of reminds us those big ringes
about like what testosterone is at right
very big ringes when you have a big
ringe like this you you want to think
what's the significance of this so
fertin basically is the iron it's a
storage molecule for ION it is where ion
gets um trapped whether it's in the
liver um so it's not and it is trapped
in its feris feric form the less toxic
form of iron so it doesn't cause so the
body really en envelopes the iron
molecule so it doesn't cause damage
that's how it gets stored in the liver
then it gets transferred into the blood
test where it's being circulated via
transfering molecule right so what's
important what's important for ferin to
know is that it both reflects iron
stores and also um inflammation because
it is what we call an acute phase
reactant meaning that if there is
inflammation or infection it will go up
so fair Partin and iron have a very
close relationship our blood tests are
not perfect um but that's what we have
so we have your total ion your tibc and
your your total ion and tibc your
transfering saturation and your fertin
we also have your hemoglobin and
hematocrit your levels were 60 and the
hematocrit were 50 and you had an MCV
mean corpuscular volume out about 89
normal is between 80 to 100 so all of
your normal numbers are within range but
when we go deeper and we're going to
focus on fertin your fertin is not in
the optimal range and what what do I
base myself to say that there was a
really interesting study it was called
The Feast Fe a St the feast study iron
Fe in atherosclerosis study and that was
done a study that was done in the late
90s um it was done out of about 24 VA
centers about 1,00 patients that they
followed for six years and those
patients had Peripheral arterial disease
they had clots they had plaque in their
legs um Venus insuff arterial
insufficiency in their leg so those were
kind of patients with atherosclerosis
already so higher risis type patients
and what the the hypothesis was because
they know that ion interacts a lot
within the atherosclerosis plaque so
that the hypothesis was by donating
blood they would improve the outcomes so
they followed about 12200 patients
average age was about 60 for about 6
years and they were doing photomy on
those patients to decrease the fertin
and the results were very interesting so
when they first publish the results they
saw that there was no no um influence of
decreasing fertin with outcomes and they
looked at two outcomes the first outcome
was death the second outcome was
non-fatal Mi stroke so whether you die
you had a heart attack or you out a
stroke those were the three outcomes
they look that so it was kind of
discouraging to see that wow okay donate
blood we had a good hypothesis it didn't
work but in 2007 they said that was late
' 90s they re they reanalyzed the data
and they found something very
interesting they said that if they
account for age the younger patients say
younger was the age 43 to 61 had a
significant um Improvement in their
Peripheral arterial disease and in the
primary and secondary outcomes which was
death heart attacks and stroke the lower
their fiting
guy it was so powerful that in
2011 in in the the magazine um um a very
famous Cardiology magazine heart
circulation they they they did the the
they they put out those findings that
then they when they re-evaluated the
stud the the data of the feast study
they show that for younger patients
that's 43 to 61 graded photomy and
bringing your fot your fair level
between 20 and 100 completely improved
all of the outcomes less incidents of
death less incidents of heart attacks
less incidence of stroke and better
results with their Peripheral arterial
disease and that is not the first study
they did on fertin and Longevity there
was another study that was done in
Finland those are a younger patient 38
and they saw also that there was a
direct linear correlation with Fittin
and Longevity and the last study that
they did I about this in our last one
was a Scandinavian study it was the
Scandinavian the Copenhagen heart study
and they looked at almost 10,000
patients for 23 years that's a big study
and they looked at a stepwise in
increase in fertin corresponds with a
lower survival age this was very simple
and they what I like is they didn't say
why your ftin was elevated but the high
ftin level was a associated with an
early earlier age of death people who
had F in 500 or more their average age
of death was in the
50s if you had 200 or less it was 79
that is a big difference and it was a
linear that's why they feel and when
they look at the fee study they're like
okay less than 200 was with the
Copenhagen heart the fee study showed
that it needs to be even lower so now if
you look at every functional medicine
recommendations based on the feast study
is that they want the fertin to be
between 20 and 100 um in that study the
feast study they looked at a Fatin of
194 positively correlated with higher
risk of heart disease high risk of
stroke high risk of cancers because
fertin and iron is is a carcinogen
carcinogenic that I'll do a talk about
these to explain how it is a c syy so if
I look at your numbers all of your
numbers good only your fertin is a
little bit outside above the normal
above the optimal functional medicine
range which would be between 20 and 100
okay now why would you donate if your
levels are quote unquote normal and you
have no symptoms from and that's the big
question again those studies show us
that a lower fertin level corresponds to
a long to to better outcomes overall and
why is because ion is such a toxic
element we've talked about this how ion
is necessary for life it is necessary to
carry oxygen level it is necessary to
catalized reactions in the electron
transport chain for the formation of ATP
within the mitochondria it's necessary
for brain development muscle development
very importantly in in your immune
system so iron is necessary for life
there's no question but too much iron
and again it is because of its oxidative
properties the fact that iron can give
electrons that's how it can create ATP
it creates a lot of junk and rust so
what I'm trying to make people
understand is a very simple
concept iron rust Metals outside
everybody can see that iron also rust
our cells in the inside so I want you to
picture when you have too much iron it's
almost like you left a metal chair
outside and you start seeing that it
starts getting rust and with time the
rusting goes deeper if eventually it
disintegrates the metal what ion does to
our cells it causes the formation of oxy
radicals reactive oxygen species and oxy
radicals are the most destructive
oxidants right we always know that we
have to take antioxidants to prevent
aging well how about decreasing the
formation of oxidants with ion so when
we manage our ion status that's what we
do we try to decrease the amount of
oxidants that we create because the way
cellular respiration happens is oxygen
comes in um goes through the electron
Trad sport chain creates ATP but by
creating ATP the other side of the coin
is that it creates oxidants it creates
fumes exhaust right it's like a car you
create energy but your body your car
creates exhaust managing the exhaust is
one of the most important things we need
to do in anti-aging or Age Management
medicine so yes you want to make more
ATP but you want to also deal with the
exhaust and the exhaust is the oxidants
formed by cellular respiration when they
combine with iron and especially they
call it non-transfer bound ion when ion
is not bound to molecules like
transferin or fertin it becomes free to
rust our cells you combine um hydrogen
peroxide which is uh which is a
byproduct of cellular respiration
hydrogen P oxide plus oxy
via the Fenton reaction because it's one
of the most destructive radicals known
it's called oh
minus the Fenton reaction causes that
radical that can destroy um DNA so
causing cancer malformation can destroy
lipid causing lipid peroxidation it
interacts with atherosclerosis plaqu
increase risk of heart disease
Peripheral arterial disease can denature
protein so this reaction is one of the
most Point reaction we need to know
about the Fenton reaction So based on
knowing that iron is a very important
oxidant that's why we want to keep your
fairity level at the at that
range